Hugh J. Paterson III

Curriculum Vitae

Address:

2675 BakerBlvd. Eugene, OR 97403 USA +1 618.567.9799 hugh.paterson@sil.org sil.linguist@gmail.com

Personal Information:

Citizenship: United States

Gender: Male Family: Married

Myers-Briggs Personalty Type: ENTP



Summary:

Hugh works for SIL International as part of the International innovation team. His work focuses on helping organizational leadership define and clarify their business goals, the kinds of audiences they are trying to serve, and how those audiences are going to experience the provided services. He specializes in leveraging technology, defining work flows, and managing digital assets to meet organizational impact goals. Hugh leverages his previous work in language documentation and his background in linguistics to provide meaningful solutions to those working in language development.

Education:

2018 M.A. student in linguistics, University of North Dakota.

2009 Guest student at the Graduate Institute of Applied Linguistics, Dallas Texas.

2007 B.A., German

Southern Illinois University Edwardsville. Undergraduate Minor: Linguistics.

Thesis: De, Der, Die, D' Definite Articles in Aargau and Thurgau

Thesis Supervisor: Asst. Prof. Douglas Simms

Education Abroad:

2006 Study in Würzburg, Germany, through Southern Illinois University Edwardsville.

1996 Gymnasium Schule, Germany.

1992 - 1993 Grundschule, Germany.

Research Interests:

- · Language documentation
- · Linguistic cartography
- · Orthography usage
- · Tone in Orthographies
- Minority language text input
- Digital Asset Management (Digital Archives)
- Austronesian historical linguistics
- · Social-linguistic & non-aural factors influencing sound change
- Phonetic articulations involving tongue protrusion
- Platform Development of research environments presenting linguistic and language data
- · User experience design
- · Accessibility & usability of research data
- · Work flow design and optimization

Positions Held:

2018- Present Innovation Analyst

SIL International: Distributed team

Identify opportunities to create customers.

Describe, plan, and report on innovation projects.

Ensure the effective execution of projects.

Manage small teams of people.

Manage project budgets.

Advise the Chief Innovation Development Officer.

2011 - 2018 Usefulness Engineer

SIL International: Distributed team

Worked with a team to bring language documentation and linguistic content to the web, creating pleasurable interactions with user.

Acted as a business consultant to organizational units in SIL to bring their services to the web.

Major areas of participation: Information Architecture, Planing, Business Analysis, User Experience Analysis.

2010 - 2012 Assistant to the Americas Area Access Coordinator SIL International: Dallas, Texas

Established archival quality digitization procedures for language documentation and minority language education materials.

Collaborated with the Language & Culture Archive to establish metadata schemas for audio and video materials, both for discovery and processing of materials through digitization workflows

Managed a team of volunteers digitizing various mediums of language documentation and cultural resources

2010 - 2011 Assistant to the Americas Area Linguistics Coordinator SIL International: Dallas, Texas

Worked with SIL staff in México doing language documentation.

Established project metadata tracking and file organization procedures for multiresearcher language documentation project.

Field Work:

2017	Uౖt-Ma'in	[gel] Kebbi State, Nigeria.
2013	Uౖt-Ma'in	[gel] Kebbi State, Nigeria.
2010 - 2011	Malinaltepec Me'phaa	[tcf] Guerrero State, Mexico.
2010 - 2011	Tlacoapa Me'phaa	[tpl] Guerrero State, Mexico.

Language Proficiency:

Native: English

Near-native fluency: German

Basic reading knowledge: Dutch, Middle High German, Swiss German, Spanish

Some knowledge: Mandarin, Nepali, Koine Greek, Hausa

Digital tools

WordPess, Drupal, Hugo, Github, Google Apps, Facebook Groups, Facebook Pages, MailChimp, Omnigraffle, Confluence, MediaWiki, FLEx, XLingPaper, Atom, Lightroom, Endnote, Zotero, Linux (Ubuntu), OS X/MacOS 10.6-10.12, Markdown, HTML, Bash

Lesser experience with: ELAN, Praat, Audacity, WeSay, SayMore, Bloom, CSS, Python, php, MySQL, XML, Microsoft Office, LibreOffice, Pro Tools, FinalCut Pro.

Teaching Experience:

2009	Teaching Assistant: (Prof. Keith Snider) LING 507 - Tone Analysis,
	University of North Dakota, Grand Forks, North Dakota
2007 - 2008	One-to-One Trainer: iLife, iWork & OS X, Apple, Inc., St. Louis, Missouri
2006	One-to-One Trainer: iLife, iWork & OS X, Apple, Inc., Lake Grove, New York
2005	Elementary German Teacher: It's a Small World, Festus, Missouri
2005	ESL Classroom Assistant: International Institute, St. Louis, Missouri
2003	Junior Achievement Teacher: St. John Newman, Maryville, Illinois

Awards and Honors:

2004 German Student of the Year Award (SIUE)

Articles 2016

2011

2010

Littauer, Richard and Hugh Paterson III. 2016. Open Source Code Serving Endangered Languages. In Soria, Claudia, et al. (eds.), In Proceedings of LREC 2016 Collaboration and Computing for Under-Resourced Languages: Towards an Alliance for Digital Language Diversity (CCURL) Workshop. Portorož, Slovenia, 23 May, pp. 86-8.

Kevin L. Cline, Stephen A. Marlett, Hugh Paterson III and Mark L. Weathers. *Las Conexiones Externas e Internas*. En: Stephen A. Marlett (ed.) Los Archivos Lingüísticos Me'phaa.

[http://www.sil.org/mexico/workpapers/WP013-PDF/MephaaConexiones.pdf]

Paterson III, Hugh J., Kenneth S. Olson, Jeff Mielke, Josephine Sanicas-Daguman & Carol Jean Pebley. *The phonetic status of the (inter)dental approximant.*Journal of the International Phonetic Association. 40.2:199-215.

Chapter (Peer Reviewed):

2014 Paterson III, Hugh J. . Keyboard layouts: Lessons from the Me'phaa and

Sochiapam Chinantec designs in Endangered Languages and New Technologies

edited by Mari C. Jones. pp. 49-66.

Articles (In Progress):

Paterson III, Hugh J. & Kenneth S. Olson. *An Unlikely Retention - the historical status of the interdental approximant.*

Paterson III, Hugh J. The socially acceptable sight of sounds.

Presentations:

2015 Phonetic transcription of tone in the IPA. Poster presented at 18th International Conference of Phonetic Sciences. Held in Glasgow, Scotland.10-14 August.

African Languages: Assessing the text input difficulty. Paper presented at the 46th Annual Conference of African Linguistics. Held at the University of Oregon 26-28. March.

Assessing the difficulty of the text input task for minority languages. Paper presented at the 4th International Conference on Language Documentation & Conservation, Ala Moana Hotel in Honolulu, HI. February 26th – March 1^{st.}

Lexical dataset archiving: an assessment of practice. Poster presented at the 4th International Conference on Language Documentation and Conservation, at the Ala Moana Hotel in Honolulu, HI. February 26th – March 1st Version 1.0.

Language archiving and data ecology. Presentation at the University of Oregon GLOSS

and the Department of Linguistics Colloquium, Eugene, OR, 23 May.

Challenges of implementing a tool to extract metadata from linguists: the use case of

RAMP. Poster presented at 3rd International Conference on Language Documentation and Conservation, at the University of Hawai'i Mānoa,

Honolulu, HI. February 28th - March 3rd.

2014

2013

2012 Keyboard layout as part of language documentation: the case of the Me'phaa and Chinantec keyboards. Paper presented at: Language Endangerment:

Methodologies and New Challenges, CRASSH Cambridge, UK. 6 July.

2011 Getting things out of FLEx: Dictionaries in multiple modes. International Workshop on

Fieldworks Software. Universiti Malaysia Sabah, 17-21 October.

2009 Lasting Linguistics: Making a Meaningful Mark. with John Clifton & Steve Marlett.

University of North Dakota 2009 linguistics colloquium series, 30 July. An Unlikely Retention. Paper presented at the 11th International Conference of

Austronesian Linguistics, 22-26 June, Aussois, France.

Repair strategies used with the interdental approximant in some Philippine languages. Presentation at the Graduate Institute of Applied Linguistics

Academic Forum, 18 May.

Guest Lectures:

2010 Guest lecture on Innate v.s Learned & The Emergence of Distinctive Features

for the Phonology I course at the University of North Dakota (UND).

2009 Guest lecture on microphone selection and use in Acoustic Phonetics course at

UND.

Guest lecture on Language Documentation in Field Methods course at UND.

2008 Guest lecture on Language Documentation in Field Methods course at UND.

Professional Associations:

Past or Present

Linguistic Society of America (LSA) [http://www.lsadc.org]
Foundation for Endangered Languages (FEL). [http://www.ogmios.org]
Audio Engineering Society [http://www.aes.org]

International Phonetic Association (IPA)

[https://www.internationalphoneticassociation.org]

Professional Contacts:

Ken Olson, Ph.D.

Associate International Linguistics Coordinator for SIL International

E-mail: ken_olson@sil.org Web: http://www.sil.org/~olsonk/

Steve Parker, Ph.D.

Assistant Professor of Applied Linguistics at GIAL

E-mail: steve_parker@gial.edu

Web: http://www.gial.edu/personnel/fac-parker.htm

Additional referees are available if required:

Fraser Bennett, Ph.D.

Director, Language Program Training SIL International

E-mail: Fraser_Bennett@sil.org

Douglas Simms, Ph.D.

Assistant Professor in German at SIUE

E-mail: dsimms@siue.edu